A Guide to the Hairston-Wilson-James Family Papers, 1764-1937
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Hairston-Wilson-James Family Papers, 1764-1937
The Library of Virginia
41196
1.8 cubic feet (4 boxes).
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Donor information unavailable.
Biographical Information
George Hairston was born in Bedford County, Virginia on 20 September 1750. He was the son of Robert Hairston and Ruth Stovall. He married Elizabeth Perkins Letcher (1759-1818) on 1 January 1781. Hairston served as a colonel in the Revolutionary War and fought at the Battle of Guilford Court House and at the siege of Yorktown. Following the war, Col. Hairston resided at his Henry County plantation "Beaver Creek." He also served as a brigadier general in the War of 1812, and commanded a brigade consisting of the 3rd, 4th, 5th, and 6th Virginia militia regiments and the North Carolina 23rd. He died on 5 March 1827.
His son Marshall Hairston was born on 4 March 1802. He married his cousin Ann Hairston (1802-1888) on 12 March 1829. They lived at "Beaver Creek" and had nine children. Marshall Hairston died on 20 January 1882.
Their daughter Ruth Stovall Hairston was born on 4 December 1837, with her twin sister Ann Marshall Hairston (1837-1907). Ruth married Robert A. Wilson (ca. 1825-1892) of "Dan's Hill" in Pittsylvania County. They had one daughter, Ann Marshall Wilson (1869-1938). Ruth Stovall Wilson died in 1886.
Ann Marshall Wilson married Rorer Anderson James (1859-1921) on 12 October 1892. He was an attorney and owner of the Danville Register and Danville Bee newspapers, member of the Virginia House of Delegates and Virginia Senate, and member of the United States House of Representatives. He died on 6 August 1921. Ann Marshall James died on 27 March 1938. They are both buried in Green Hill Cemetery in Danville.
Scope and Content
Papers, 1764-1937, of the Hairston, Wilson, and James family of Henry and Pittsylvania Counties, Danville, and Martinsville, Virginia, and Mississippi, namely Col. George Hairston (1750-1825), Ann Hairston (1802-1888), Ann Marshall Hairston (1837-1907), Col. Robert Wilson (1789-1873), Robert A. Wilson (ca. 1825-1892), Ruth Stovall (Hairston) Wilson (1837-1886), Rorer A. James (1859-1921), and Ann Marshall (Wilson) James (1869-1938). The collection includes accounts and receipts, agreements, catalogs and price lists, correspondence, invitations and announcements, ledgers of John S. Townes (1854-1900), photographs, rent ledgers, scrapbook, and logs detailing work performed at the Wilson properties "Hickory Forest" and "Dan's Hill."
The earliest letters in the collection are written to Col George Hairston and concern legal and financial matters, post office duties, the death of his son Nicholas Perkins Hairston (1791-1822), and the administration of the estate of another son Henry Hairston (1793-1825) in Mississippi. There are letters written to Col. Robert Wilson from his son William Wilson while he was attending Emory and Henry College in 1856, and a letter from his son Robert A. Wilson while he was stationed with troops at the fairgrounds in Richmond in 1861. There are numerous letters written by Ann Hairston to her granddaughter Ann Marshall Wilson covering the period 1877 to 1884, and there are also letters written by Ruth Hairston Early (1849-1928) that include numerous references to her uncle Jubal A. Early (1816-1894). The collection also includes correspondence from Ruth Stovall Wilson and Annie Marshall Wilson to Robert A. Wilson while they were attending the World's Industrial and Cotton Centennial Exposition in New Orleans in 1885.
Other items of note in the collection include agreements, or labor contracts, between Robert A. Wilson and various individuals. Most are from the 1880's. There is a bank book of Robert Wilson with the Farmers Bank of Virginia, covering the period 1848 to 1861, an 1850-1851 catalog from the Patapsco Female Institute, Richmond and Danville Railroad Company stock receipts, 1848-1850, and a scrapbook of Rorer A. James that includes a letter from Woodrow Wilson.
Contents List
- Accounts and Receipts, 1829-1921, undated. (Box 1, Folder 1-32)
- Agreements. (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Baldwin & Co. Fertilizers. (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Bank Book - Farmers Bank of Virginia, 1848-1861. (Box 1, Folder 36)
- E.D. Bassford. (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Daniel F. Beatty Pianos and Organs. (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Broadside - Trustee's Sale, 1888. (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Business/Calling/Trade Cards. (Box 1, Folder 40)
- Cancelled Checks, 1865, 1898. (Box 1, Folder 41)
- Check Register, 1895-1896. (Box 1, Folder 42)
- Clippings. (Box 1, Folder 43)
- Columbus Commercial (Columbus, Miss.), 16 January 1919. (Box Personal Papers Oversize Box 105)
- Correspondence, 1808-1917. (Box 2, Folder 1-37)
- Correspondence, 1918-1932, undated. (Box 3, Folder 1-8)
- Danville Military Institute Application (Blank). (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Danville Register, 9 February 1870. (Box Personal Papers Oversize Box 105)
- Deeds. (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Fallon Florist Price List. (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Fee Bills. (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Furness Bermuda Line - Steamship Fort Victoria Saloon Plan. (Box Oversize Personal Papers Box 105)
- Good Cheer (Greenfield, Mass.), April 1886. (Box Oversize Personal Papers Box 105)
- Greeting Cards. (Box 3, Folder 13)
- House of Representatives Member's Passes. (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Insurance Policy, 1895. (Box Oversize Personal Papers Box 105)
- Introduction of William Jennings Bryan. (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Invitations/Announcements. (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Ledger - John S. Townes, 1891-1892. (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Ledger - John S. Townes, 1897. (Box 3, Folder 18)
- List of Books. (Box 3, Folder 19)
- Medical College of Virginia Bulletin, September 1937. (Box 3, Folder 20)
- Membership Certificate - Union Library Association. (Box Oversize Personal Papers Box 105)
- Memorandum Book. (Box 3, Folder 21)
- Miscellaneous. (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Motor Vehicle Law in Virginia, 1919. (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Muster Fine, 1852. (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Natural Bridge Tourist Booklet. (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Patapsco Female Institute Catalogue, 1850-1851. (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Patapsco Guano Company (Memorandum Book), 1915. (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Photographs. (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Promissory Notes. (Box 4, Folder 8)
- The Relation of High Schools and Colleges to the Improvement of Rural Life by John Preston McConnell. (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Rent Ledger, 1887-1891. (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Rent Ledger, 1889-1890. (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Report Cards. (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Restoration of Voting Rights (Act), 1865. (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Richmond and Danville Railroad Company Stock Receipts, 1848-1850. (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Sandy River Bridge. (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Scrapbook, 1916-1920. (Box 4, Folder 16)
- Slave Division. (Box 4, Folder 17)
- Speech - State Democratic Convention, undated. (Box 4, Folder 18)
- Suit Papers. (Box 4, Folder 19)
- Surveys. (Box 4, Folder 20)
- The Taxation of Intangibles in Virginia by George Bryan, 1917. (Box 4, Folder 21)
- Taxes. (Box 4, Folder 22)
- Tickets. (Box 4, Folder 23)
- Virginia Nurseries - Order, 1884. (Box 4, Folder 24)
- Vote Certification - House of Delegates, 1891. (Box 4, Folder 25)
- Work Log - Joseph H. Gray, 1883. (Box 4, Folder 26)
- Work Log - Joseph Watson Brown, 1891. (Box 4, Folder 27)